[Music]
thank you
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to this special midweek
episode of the ask Abhijit show uh I'm
traveling this week and that's why we
are doing it in midweek because one
should not miss any live streams so uh I
hope you are all doing very well and as
always before we begin let me uh greet
you on let's see who all is there in the
live chat I can see G film Naman panchal
Mohit jp112 Aman George costov
palmak shivansh Mythic boy
changes Modi DK boss techie Matos
World Vladimir Putin is here Durga good
evening
Vivek Mao Zedong comrade hello comrade
om strangely proton hush Jain
Bharat Swami Adolf is their geopolitical
Dubai jitendra Bharat First Alpha
Nishant ayush ashwani Sharma
Aryan Sharma India Unleashed Mr Giga
chart of India dealing
Kamal
Bharat first
just manraj Singh Melvin shubham lucky
JK xp1101 Vishnu Mohan and lone Rider
Priyanka swapna shivagami Devi
teaching Abhishek bhupesh good evening
good day to all of you
uh so many of you thank you so much for
being on this live stream in the middle
of the week and uh with that done I'm
sorry I cannot greet all of you there
just too many but yeah let's get into
the questions and let's see what we have
today let's uh Where Do We Begin let's
begin here
okay let's begin with turkey
tanvi says what would be the effect on
India's relations with turkey and
India's image in the world due to
India's immediate help to Turkey which
supports Pakistan stand on Kashmir and
repeatedly in Pakistan's refusing to use
the airspace and all and it says Aditya
says this is a far-fetched optimistic
question but do you think that
humanitarian Aid towards a collaborative
country could change its perspective
towards the aider in which case we're
talking about India and turkey relations
and given the complexities Armenia
Cyprus Etc that are already entailed
with it all right good question so so
what is happening India is definitely
aiding turkey and India is doing a I
mean sending significant Aid to Turkey
as we know turkey has recently been
devastated by a series of earthquakes
two major ones uh well above seven on
the on the on the moment scale Richter
Scale whichever it is very major
earthquakes and lots of trucks it's been
a humanitarian disaster total tragedy
lots of towns and cities have been wiped
out I mean you know we see all these
videos of buildings crumbling and
falling and people trapped in the rubble
terrible situation in Turkey it's winter
it's freezing it's snowing in many
places bad bad situation so India has
been one of the first Nations to respond
and India is sending significantly let's
take a look at what kind of Aid India is
sending to
turkey
let's see well let's take a look at this
so I'm going to put some tweets by
siddhant sibal who is a journalist on
the screen so India names its relief and
rescue operation to help turkey and
Syria as operation those fine that's
good
sixth Indian military plane which is
with relief reaches quick hit turkey
this is in the morning today this is an
Indian military plane in turkey and uh
Indian this is uh the people who are
departing in the plane military
personnel ndrf people and all that
so this is what's happening sent more
than 250 Personnel specialized equipment
the relief material amounting to more
than 135 tons to Turkey on 5c 17 iaf
aircraft and this is the sixth one here
so you can see how significant the aid
is and all the details are there now uh
Indian Rescue of efforts
and field Hospital in Turkey so you can
see Indian medical personnel are already
operate or already deployed there they
are helping out the people who are
affected by the terror but the
earthquake
you can see that uh already going on
this is from the Indian army as you can
see the Turkish uh civilians who are
being helped by the Indian
medical personnel another person are
really thankful very grateful it's good
it's very good Indian ndrf team in
rescue operations
turkey uh you can see this is a very
dangerous job and Indians are putting
their lives on the line to to help uh
the unfortunate people who have been
affected by this complete disaster this
is very dangerous work yes uh then what
else Indian military teams in turkey
with humanitarian assistance in the
aftermath the earthquake this is from
yesterday so there's a whole you know uh
operation that's going on from within
India and uh India's India if Turkey the
city was the epicenter of the earthquake
that struck the country earlier this
week and you can see all these efforts
are ongoing
so that's what India is doing what else
do we have
and India humanitarian assistance also
reaches Damascus Syria so we are sending
Aid to Turkey as well as to Syria so
this is uh we saw all the images from
turkey and these are images from Syria
this is Damascus Airport
so we have uh handed over Indian relief
to the local one of the local ministers
uh so that's what India is doing this is
very significant help in India has
responded with great alacrity India is
first of all showing to the world that
not only can we take care of our own
country but as and one required we can
immediately send significant assistance
to other nations irrespective of where
they stand on the geopolitical Spectrum
whether they are our friends
you know friendly towards India or
aligned with India's enemies doesn't
matter this is a humanitarian thing and
we need to help people
so that's what India is doing that's the
background to these questions that have
been asked and obviously it cost a lot
of money which comes from the Indian
taxpayers uh expense right uh so the
question is all of this
that India is doing will it what would
the what would be the effect of this or
India's relationship with turkey and
India's image in the world
overall so first of all the Turks the
civilians who are helped by this they
will certainly feel an enormous amount
of gratitude those who are those who are
impacted by the Indian Aid and the
Indian medical personnel and the ndrf
Personnel who are rescuing people all of
this will create good will think about
Afghanistan think about uh the the fact
that India has for the past two plus
decades spent like
I don't know how many billions of
dollars in Aid to Afghanistan in
developing the nation so in see the U.S
what the U.S did was it bombed thousands
of pounds of democracy on Afghanistan
soil and then it funneled in billions of
dollars of hundreds of millions of
dollars in Aid or assistance whatever
you want to call it but that money went
to the corrupt politicians it helped the
Americans buy the corrupt politicians
and that's how they they operated a
puppet government in Afghanistan as long
as there is the is the rule the nation
The Americans
now India also says
invested more than a billion dollars in
Afghanistan but that money was not given
to the corrupt politicians that money
was used for actual building and
rebuilding efforts we built dams we
built the parliament we build hospitals
libraries roads all these things we
invested we sent money for agricultural
projects so all of this actually helped
the common man woman and child in
Afghanistan we have been doing this for
more than two decades and as a result of
this sustained effort even the Taliban
is not
they may want perhaps but they are
incapable of seeing India as an enemy
and whether they admit it or not they
feel warmth and gratitude towards India
even the talibandhu because even the
Taliban their family members have been
helped and they they have been impacted
positively by what India is doing so if
you do this over an extended period of
period of time without asking for
anything in return it is impossible not
for the recipient of your Aid to feel
gratitude
towards you so Afghanistan we know very
well even under the Taliban the enmity
is with Pakistan and the Taliban seeks
India as a benefactor and is a friendly
Nation
and they have been cooperating with
India in all kinds of ways the Taliban
especially with the Indian embassies and
consulates in Afghanistan and the rescue
of various people and all those things
so now if we since we are doing this
with turkey see it's not going to be a
sustained effort we're not going to
invest billions of dollars in Turkey for
20 plus years that's not going to happen
we are doing this as a one-time thing
because they are in need of they are in
desperate need of help from wherever it
comes so we are doing this it will
certainly create a certain amount of
Goodwill in Turkey as long as it is
publicized properly sometimes we do a
lot of good work but we never let the
world know so this time we have Twitter
the Indian government is active on
Twitter it is disseminating information
we have journalists who are also
disseminating the information about what
India is doing
so hold on
this will create a certain amount of
change in the way the Turks regard India
historically the Turkish people in the
Turkish government have been very
anti-india I would not say the Turkish
people are very anti-india but they they
certainly are pro-pakistan and when you
are pro-pakistan it's natural for you to
be anti-india there's a religious angle
to it and all that but when this Aid
comes in it's going to create some good
will at a certain extent and this will
spread through Word of Mouth in Turkey
by through those who are helped by India
and you can see those images that they
don't they speak for themselves so
there's going to be a certain amount of
Goodwill in Turkey among the people the
government of turkey and Mr erdogan they
have their own geopolitical agenda
that's not going to change your
geopolitical imperatives and agenda and
and constraints they are all dictated by
geography
and history
so if you look at the geography in
history we know that turkey no matter
how much we help them the government and
the leadership of turkey will have their
own
specific uh geopolitical and
geostrategic Ambitions which which
essentially right now is to create a new
version of the Ottoman Empire
that's what Mr erdogan is working
towards that's not going to change and
if he wants to create a Neo Ottoman
Empire kind of situation he will need
the the help of Nations other nations
clearly India will not support that so
they will obviously have to take support
from Pakistan because Pakistan has this
thing right they need and daddy
somewhere else the Arabs have refused to
be Pakistan's daddies another one the
the one turkey to be the daddy
and turkey will use that for their own
benefit so from a big picture
geopolitical perspective it will not
change much uh but from a
people-to-people thing kind of thing
there will be a little amount of a
certain amount a limited amount of
Goodwill in Turkey towards India and if
it is publicized properly and the Turks
really see that then it may be it may
spread a little more
as a one-time a one-time thing typically
over time gets forgotten if you do it
for two decades plus then it is hard for
anyone to forget that so this will
create a few few ripples of Goodwill in
Turkey let's not be overly optimistic
now what about India's uh image in the
world it will certainly uh embellish in
burnish India's image in the world India
has been doing this for a very long time
helping people out when the Afghanistan
thing happened the Americans withdrew
overnight from Afghanistan lots of
people were stranded in Afghanistan
including U.S citizens in India like I
said India has a great amount of
Goodwill among even belong with the
Taliban that is something India was able
to leverage the Taliban made sure that
no Indian is harmed even while they were
in the business in the process of
capturing the city of Kabul in taking
over Kabul even in that situation they
ensured that no Indian is harmed and
Indians who are in the Indian government
officials were trying to rescue people
and take them out of the country will be
allowed to do it and no questions will
be asked so India rescued Turks from
there India rescued a bunch of Americans
and people or people of other nations
this is something that's on the record
India has also have been been offering
assistance for the covet thing to
various countries and our systems for
free not sending Aid and then asking for
money the Americans when they send Aid
that typically ask for money when they
say we are sending military aid to to
Taiwan they're actually getting money
from Taiwan it's not Aid they're selling
weapons so India sent a lot of
assistance to lots of nations in terms
of vaccine or other things in India did
not take money for that so all of these
actions and India obviously there have
been lots of other uh other such
situations India has been operating uh
involved in anti-piracy operations uh
India rescued lots of people from Yemen
when things went bad so India does this
uh without expecting anything in return
and overall over a period of time over a
long period of time if you do it in a
sustained manner the world notices and
this becomes something that becomes part
of your let's say reputation uh
marketers would call it you could call
it your brand yes it becomes part of
your reputation India becomes India is
in the process of becoming a acquire
this reputation of
being able to uh undertake such
difficult operations and being willing
as a nation that's willing to offer Aid
to anybody who requires it which is a
good thing so it's certainly going to uh
embellish and burnish India's image
internationally obviously the West will
not publicize this
because they they don't it's not in
their when it's not it's not good for
them if a nation like India poor third
world nation Etc starts become a major
becoming a major player on the global
stage but that's what's happening so the
West may not publicize it you will not
see any Washington Post or Guardian
articles written about whatever India is
doing about the fact that India is
helping turkey in its time of desperate
need the Washington Post will not write
about it the New York Times the guardian
they won't try to think about it all
just there are also most likely
motivated about that what about this but
social media bypasses all these
Gatekeepers so yes it's going to be uh
it's going to be noticed and it's it all
of this adds incrementally to India's
reputation uh what else will India and
turkey relations improve because of this
not not quite I mean it will it will
become a little harder for Mr erdogan to
be empty India little slightly slightly
harder but after all geostrategic
imperatives are geostrategic imperative
so it will not uh change much uh in the
terms of the India turkey relationship
at a at a global level at a geopolitical
level but overall it is good for India's
image and India is doing this without
expecting anything in return India is
not doing this as a image building
experience India is genuinely offering
help and it it has a reputation it has a
long track record of offering help uh
without strings attached so that's uh
what India is doing and it is a very
good thing
nikhil says recently Ukrainian lawmakers
asked the United States to sanction
India and China because we keep buying
Russian oil so will this statement
affect India Ukraine relations
well it is true that Ukrainian lawmakers
or whoever it is I heard about this they
have asked the U.S uh to sanction India
to impose sanctions of India because
India is buying Russian oil the
Americans obviously have not reserved
they have said that no such thing will
happen the India U.S relationship is
very important in the obvious focus of
that is towards China the U.S needs
India to counterbalance China that's how
the balance of power works
in geopolitics and especially on the
Asian Eurasian chess board so the
Americans are not in a position to
sanction India and they will not
sanction India the question other other
question is will this uh will this call
for sanctions affect India Ukraine
relations
let's understand
Ukraine
foreign policy and internal policy now
I'm sure you've heard me say this that
Ukraine has transformed itself into a
U.S vasal state
I use the French pronunciation of basala
so when you are
a vasal of of an Overlord what does it
really mean
it means that you have outsourced policy
to your overlord you have outsourced
your foreign policy to your overload you
ask outsourced your economic policy to
your overlord and you've outsourced some
parts of your internal policy also to
your own Lord so you are nominally
independent you can have elections as
long as the elections go in the right
direction and all that but at the end of
the day you are controlled by an
external power that's what Ukraine is
that's what Pakistan is that's what what
most of the EU and NATO nations are
they are all vasals of the United States
so when Ukraine
when when it's in a position in a
situation that it's foreign policy is
entirely controlled and dictated by by
the United States what does it mean it
means that India Ukraine relations are
actually India U.S relations
okay so if the ukrainians have made this
call
to sanction India it means that also has
been instigated by somewhere in by
somewhere in the in the in the U.S uh
apparatus
whenever a foreign policy statement is
made from Ukraine it most likely
originates outside Ukraine and it is
Ukraine is like a sock puppet so the
Americans obviously want to to keep on
pressuring India uh their formal
official statements will be that we
respect India as a sovereignty and
Independence and we need India on our
side and all that but indirectly they
will keep on running this campaign they
have these this this enormous multitude
of disposable Minions on social media
you know think tank experts and
journalists and all that they have all
these media Publications like the
guardian the New York Times Washington
Post what not I'll maybe Al Jazeera as
well uh and all that and various other
European
uh Publications and all that so they use
all of this to keep pressuring India but
that official statement that comes from
the uh from the state department is that
we respect India sovereignty and uh
India is an indispensable partner
so understand this please that India
Ukraine relations are actually Ukraine
is just a proxy their foreign policy is
entirely
controlled by the U.S
so India Ukraine relations are actually
India U.S relations there is no there is
no Ukraine as such you could there is
you know Ukraine a quarter of it is
already gone gone
and uh who knows where Ukraine will be
in the next couple of years maybe maybe
12 months maybe 24 months we have no
idea so Ukraine so India Ukraine
relations don't matter
that's what I'm trying to say
it's India U.S relations that matter
so yeah it doesn't matter what the
Eucharist say ukrainians say you have to
understand what is being signaled
through that Ukraine is merely a proxy
of a larger power which is the U.S
what are your thoughts on India's budget
allocation to neighbors recently
especially Afghanistan you said it's a
strategic move because we have to deal
with the Taliban because our
International
considering recently attacks by the
tahrike
Pakistan on various Pakistani uh
institutions Army Etc all that
is
separate from the Afghan Taliban that is
currently in control of afghanatha
it's a separate organization they have
had their own conflicts and Scribe uh of
course the overall objective of the
theories
from Pakistan and and reintegrate it
with Afghanistan and yeah it's
designated as a terrorist organization
the Pakistani military and government uh
they fight it the Pakistani Taliban and
all that so when we are investing money
in Afghanistan it has nothing to do with
the Pakistani Taliban all right that's
the first thing so India uh let's let's
see what how much exactly India is
investing let's take a look do we have
it somewhere let's let's uh
put that on the screen let's go to Karma
press
give me a second let me put that on the
screen all right so this is an Afghan
media Outlet it's called the karma press
lots of ads India announces rupees 200
crore development aid for Afghanistan
and budget 2023-24
so as part of India's budget we have
allocated 200 crore rupees for uh
for development so we're gonna use that
money to to undertake development
projects in Afghanistan
25 million dollars at the student rule
so okay I don't remember what exactly
the conversion is but that's how it is
so this is the second year that India
has continued its support since the
Taliban took control of Afghanistan the
first announcement was made in last
year's budget the internal government
which means the Taliban government
welcomed India's announcement we
appreciate India's support from for
Afghanistan's development it will help
to improve ties and trust between the
two Nations said suhail Shaheen uh the
former iea negotiations team member
within the past two decades in most
Indian assistant encompasses
infrastructure projects humanitarian
assistance education and capacity
development and small and
community-based projects so none of this
money that India is sending to
Afghanistan is going to be used to line
the pockets of corrupt politicians it's
actually going straight to the
Grassroots to the people of Afghanistan
uh in addition New Delhi has repeatedly
emphasized historical ties between the
two countries and said wheat and
vaccines during covid-19 pandemic to the
people of Afghanistan
oh okay so that's the deal
so we are what we are doing is the money
that we are allocating in our budget to
the to Afghanistan
will benefit the people of Afghanistan
it's going to benefit the Grassroots
it's not going to benefit the Taliban
the Afghan volleyball and it has nothing
to do with the Pakistani Taliban the TTP
Taliban Pakistan so we are continuing to
invest in Afghanistan
and it's going to it's not going to
enrich the Taliban who are ruling the
country it's going to help their family
members Taliban are what questions right
the 99 pursues and their families live
all across Afghanistan in most parts of
this money this development Aid will
help them
so yes the Taliban definitely welcomes
this move it's it's good for Afghanistan
it continues over our
friendly and you could say a special
relationship with Afghanistan
it's a long-term investment of course
any money that you send to as Aid or
whatever to another Nation you it there
is an element of self-interest also in
it that's simply how geopolitics works
of course we have this historical
relationship with Afghanistan it is
after all it was historically part of
India the people there are our blood
relatives so uh we are helping them and
the objective is to strengthen the
nation
and long term we want to reconnect with
Afghanistan whenever we get our
territory back temporarily it's outside
temporarily uh so it's a it's a
strategic move but it's a long-term
investment in the nation and of course
we uh the there is a very serious
territorial dispute between Afghanistan
and Pakistan it doesn't matter who's in
power in Afghanistan the territorial
dispute persists then it is the the of
gods rightfully claim
ethnicity have historically lived there
for for centuries so it should actually
belong to Afghanistan the roots of this
conflict obviously go back to the
British times when they they created the
longer the Duran line
so yes that is the situation our
interest lies in Afghanistan we would
like to see a strong Afghanistan not a
strong Pakistan
nothing against the people of Pakistan
have to keep repeating myself but yes I
have nothing against the people of
Pakistan but the Pakistani government is
a terrorist regime and it needs to be
eventually or dismantled and the people
of Pakistan their aspirations need to be
fulfilled send the one's Independence
wants Independence uh wants Independence
Punjab well we'll see about that the
Kashmir will give birth
they have been conducting this massive
demonstrations uh the Mind demanding
reunification with with the with the
motherland with the rest of Kashmir you
know inside India not inside Pakistan so
all this is happening and we have to
play this game it's a long-term game and
that's what India is doing and India is
on the right track when it comes to
these matters
Gandhi says what would be the impact of
a possible volcanic eruption in Barren
Island on the great nicobar Islands
project and India's rise as a major
power many regions of India are prone to
earthquakes aren't rising sea levels a
major problem for India what should we
do okay lots of questions inside one
let's talk about the baron Island let's
let's go to the map because to
understand where Baron island is we need
to see the map all right my favorite
thing on the screen the map where's the
map where's the map here's the map
here it is okay do we all know where
Baron island is let's let's try and
locate it this is the globe let's go to
the uh the Bay of Kalinga and we have
the Andaman and nicobar archipelago
all right over here so we're gonna go to
the northern part of this the Andaman
Islands and now we can see a couple of
dots
so India India has two volcanoes one is
narcondam which is a
a dormant volcano or maybe some people
would classify it as an extinct volcano
perhaps because it's not adopted in like
several million years perhaps so
narkundam is either an extinct or a
dormant volcano and the other one is
Baron Island which is an active worker
so let's see which is which which one is
this this is narcon dumb let's take a
look at what it looks like the
Topography of the island so you can see
it's it's a volcanic island you can see
the The Volcano but it's not active you
know it's it's there is no crater
I mean there is the remains of a crater
but it's been totally covered over with
vegetation and other things because it's
been asleep for a very long time let's
see the other one narconda we dealt with
and let's see Baron Island which is very
different from okay let's take a look at
that
satellite image all right here we see a
Caldera we can see an actual volcano and
this erupts from time to time on a
reasonably routine basis I think last
time it properly erupted was in 2020.
so as far as I know that we have two
volcanoes one is asleep for a very long
time but this one Baron island is active
it's an active volcano and it's part of
the what we what we call the ring of
fire do we know what the ring of fire is
let me let's let me put that on the
screen one second give me a second ring
of fire
Ring of Fire it is an extremely
seismically and volcanically active
region let's put some images on the
screen so that we get to see where it is
the Ring of Fire
so this is the ring of fire
it's a volcanically in seismically
active it's it's all these tectonic
faults the Andes and the Rockies in the
in the Americas are part of it uh then
we have the entire Aleutian Islands
chain Japan is part of that the current
islands are part of that all the way to
the Philippines and all the way up to
Java Sumatra Indonesia and down south up
to New Zealand New Zealand has
earthquakes on a pretty routine basis
um and we have major earthquakes in
Japan we have the the Kobe earthquake
and obviously the
2011 uh earthquake which was an absolute
disaster nine point something on the
rich scale and one was it and uh
to the West we have the andamans we have
the Andaman Sumatra earthquake in 2004
which was one of the major one of the
largest strongest earthquakes ever
recorded I think it is third in the list
I believe 9.3 on the scale
so this is the uh ring of fire this is a
different image of that and you can see
it extends all the way to the undermans
so Baron island is part of that now the
ring of fire it has some really major
volcanoes I can think of
uh
Krakatoa
Indonesia means son of Krakatoa
we have tambura so Tambora and krakato
are have erupted in the past two 300
years extraordinarily massively uh when
the Krakatoa erupted about in the 19th
century I think the the sound Was Heard
across the world
yeah it sounded like cannon fire in
India that explosion that eruption so we
have very strong powerful volcanoes in
the in this region so the question so
that is the background to this question
that's been asked now let's go back to
the map where is our map
so now the question is the impact of
volcanic eruption at Baron island or the
great nicobar Islands project well this
volcano keeps erupting and there is no
impact unless it goes completely Kaboom
like krakato or Tambora which it is not
likely to do because it doesn't have a
history of violent explosive eruptions
it erupts in a leisurely sedentary
manner uh so Inc and and let's say a
distance between uh
see the great nicobar Islands project is
down south it's in the island of great
nicobar that's the distance between
between uh Baron Island and
great nicobar let's measure the distance
measure distance and go all the way to
this place here somewhere here that is
600 and approximately 600 kilometers
that's a long distance away
so even if it explodes it erupts
reasonably explosively
the worst that can happen is possibly a
tsunami and that the two uh we're going
to most likely uh build this project in
such a way that it will be hopefully
sheltered from potential tsunamis all
this will be considered because this
region is seismically active the
engineers will definitely
break all this into consideration
so a possible volcanic eruption will not
really affect this project much
yes many regions of India are prone to
earthquakes we know that the Himalayan
region is very seismically active India
is still slamming into as as we speak
right now in real time India is still
slamming into the Eurasian uh plate and
the Himalayas are extremely unstable uh
you get earthquakes all the time we
recently had the terrible Nepal
earthquake uh a few decades ago we had
an earthquake in tarkashi I believe
Kutch has been seismically active for a
long time because that is part of the
entire process the tectonic plates
movement process
so uh and in Northeast India when we
come to the Far East of India uh
nagaland Manipur arunachal Assam all the
region there you have earthquakes
reasonably frequently there so that is
just something they have to deal with
this is the planet we have born on this
is the region that is ours we have to
adapt to the peculiarities of this
region the Japanese
they deal with it on a routine basis
they have volcanoes that eat up from
time to time they have earthquakes
almost weekly or maybe almost daily in
Japan they they just deal with it
so India also has to do about the to
deal with this we need to ensure that
whatever
important infrastructure and other
projects we're working on should uh
incorporate elements of earthquake
resistance so that's uh I'm sure what
the Indian Engineers will be doing they
will be keeping all this in mind uh sea
levels yes it's a problem in the long
term
he now says I recently did An ancestry
test the results were quite bizarre
apparently I've got West Asian ancestry
as well as Scandinavian Irish and
Finnish ancestry apart from what they
call South Asian and she has uploaded
this on her Channel how accurate are
these tests and so do they prove the
so-called indo-aryan migration let's go
to the map and take a look at these
regions West Asia all that the south
Asia nonsense annoying there's no such
thing as South Asia it's the Indian
subcontinent anyway so she has West
Asian ancestry which is uh the
Mesopotamia region west of Iran and
including today's Iraq Syria all that
that's what they call West West Asia uh
so she has some vegetation ancestry as
well as Scandinavian ancestry which
means uh the Nordic Nation Sweden Norway
Denmark Finland that region also Irish
and Finnish so Ireland is all the way
here this island west of England that's
Ireland so what what do these results
mean I'm assuming that this lady is is
Indian
so why does she have all this West Asian
and Scandinavian Irish and Finnish
ancestry does this prove that the RN
inversion theory is or migration theory
is correct
so
what they do the geneticists is that
they assign certain tags to certain
lineages yeah there is something called
uh
Iranian ancestry in our Iranian
hunter-gatherer industry so when this
tag is attached to a certain lineage
it's it makes a
the layperson
feel that that ancestry sprung out of
the ground in that place so when they
say you have some a certain percentage
of West Asian ancestry you are made to
feel as if that ancestry sprang out of
the ground of West Asia
started there it did not originate
individuals when they say it's Irish
ancestry you will feel like that that
ancestry originated from the soil of
Ireland as if it grows on trees
and finish and all that
see if you look at the
people of Ireland let's let's take a
look at let's let's just talk about
haplogroups not about the autosomal
ancestry uh and all that when you look
at the uh
why chromosomal genetics the patrilineal
genetics of Ireland it is overwhelmingly
r1b
now R1 B is descendant of R1 which most
likely
has Indian origin the results still have
to be published but it is most likely
going to be Indian ancestry the work is
still going on it is waiting to be
published
R itself which is the parent of R1 and
R2
is of Indian origin it originated in
India and obviously the ancestry of that
origin is in Africa
so all as to the best of our knowledge
all human ancestry originated in Africa
there was an Out of Africa migration
about 80 000 between 1870 000 years
before today and then these people or
ancestors they migrated along the
coastline and eventually ended up in
India and from India they migrated to
various parts of the world haplogroup f
is the oldest non-african patrilineal
lineage and it is ancestral to all these
Irish Scandinavian Finnish West Asian
ancestry
okay haplogroup f is ancestral to all
these other non-african ancestories that
is the petroleum petrolineal lineages
when it comes to matrilineal lineages
haplogroups M and N both originated in
India about 70 000 years ago 65 000
years ago and their ancestral to 95 plus
of non-african female lineages all
across the world
so when someone says you when your test
result says that you have Scandinavian
and sister in all you have to ask
yourself what is the ancestry of this
Scandinavian ancestry
it it today you will find it in
Scandinavia but where did it come from
it's now in Scandinavia but its
ancestors came from somewhere else
well I can guarantee you 65 000 years
ago its ancestors were in India and I
could I most likely
much closer to that if R if the r
lineage originates in India some 20 to
30 000 years ago it means that the most
of the people of Ireland their ancestry
was in India
some 20 to 30 000 years ago that's how
it is so these this all this terminology
is quite confusing it is very misleading
yes
so if you have some West Asian ancestry
some Scandinavian ancestry some Irish
and some finish it means that those
genetic components are found in India
itself they are integral to India itself
because not everybody
see all the people who have let's say
Irish ancestry they do not all migrate
to Ireland some of them would have
stayed behind elsewhere in the original
place
so they carry those genetics and the
some people in the original in the place
of origin also will carry those genetics
and maybe you're one of them and now
they are tagging it as Irish even though
it's it is it is something that has
originated in India so that's how it is
these tags that they assign are
extremely misleading I'm not saying they
are lying to you it means that most
people who have this sort of genetics
currently live in Ireland or or
Scandinavia or Finland or West Asia but
there is very little research that's
been done into India's genetics thus far
what we know is that India has the
highest amount of genetic diversity
anywhere in the world outside of Africa
and despite that or our genetics are
more or less uniform which is a very
strange conundrum it's it's kind of It
kind of reminds you of the cliche of
unity and diversity right
yeah
so it doesn't mean you have foreign
ancestry it means that India's genetics
are incredibly incredibly diverse and
your ancestry comes from various genetic
lineages from within India itself which
are correlated which are related to
those foreign lineages because most
likely those foreign lineages originated
long long ago in the Indian subcontinent
that is what it means
okay
Malhotra says pashtoons are descended
from Persians okay all right if you say
so uh they were mostly zoroastrians
before islamization
okay that's what you're saying my mother
is a restaurant good to know she looks
like Pakistani cricketer Miss Baul haq
she's not from an ordinary when he was
young she's not from an ordinary Persian
tribe the Persians are not tribes
he's not from whatever she calls Persian
threat but a noble Arc I came in a
person Indian zoroastrings are not from
the influential Persian tribes I'm not
sure if there's a question here but
let's take a look at Mr MS bawlak Miss
Bach
I remember that guy
and that's uh put that on the screen so
her mom looks uh like misbah UL haq
uh
okay I I'm sure it's not these images
do we have a picture of this
person when he was younger
okay here is a clean shaven version Imam
looks like this
maybe this
okay
right is it in this gentleman I'm not
sure
I do remember this guy playing that
extraordinary shot in 2007 which gave
India the World Cup thank you so much
sir Mr misbah
um
and so on all right so let's take this
off the screen it's uh right okay your
mom looks like him maybe when he was
younger maybe all right
see
the pashtoons we want to understand the
the this entire uh comment is about
pashtoons
your mom says okay so Russian all right
uh let's let's take a look at the uh the
genetics of the pashtoons let's do that
let's uh find it let's Google it and all
that there must be some
um genetic studies let's find one from
plus one and let's put that on the
screen
all right this is a research paper from
2012 about a decade old Afghanistan's
ethnic groups share a y chromosomal
Heritage structured by historical events
all right all right but fine let's
search for India
I guess
uh this is the introduction which is all
good and all fine bactrians and Pathways
and Indians of the modern Dynasty All
That Greeks are Indians and all that etc
etc
North India
next India
or cold
right
so here look look here we're looking at
the results it says haplogroups
orthoctors means or a native to India L
m20h m69 r2a Etc were found more in
pashtoons and tajiks than in uzbeks and
hazaras
so for students typically have 20 of
these three haplo groups twenty percent
of persons have the these three
one of these three haplo groups
and then uzbeks also have significant
percentage oh sorry tajiks also have
about 20 tarjis are supposed to be
Persian origin people but there you go
they have Indian oil because 20 is not a
whole lot uh
here we see that uh more details about
the structure of Afghanistan population
shows that the Afghan Pashto and tajik
are closer to north and west Indians
than to other Afghans Hazara and uzbeks
the tajiks and pastoons are much closer
to Northern Indians and western Indians
people
or else
uh
put uh there is a significant Affinity
between North Indian and West Indian
populations
creating an Afghan Indian population
structure that excludes and South Indian
providians because okay interesting
in addition Gene flew to Afghanistan
from India was marked by these three
lineages that we spoke about before
and all that
so and this is interesting
in addition the three of guns that
identified their ethnicity as Arab had
lineages that were native to India well
I think this uh
this is seen in Afghanistan not only in
Pakistan as having as wanting a foreign
Daddy but also in Afghanistan so they
are claiming that they are Arabs but
their lineages were Indian
right so
the pashtoons are not descended from
Persians let me correct you I just
showed you some evidence of that there
is a lot more you can do your own
research if you are able to read
genetics papers
where students are not descended from
Pursuits pashtoots are part of the
extended Northern Indian population
the city of Kandahar a thousand years
ago was known as a city of rajputs
so that's the deal your mom may look
like Miss bahul lock and see the
portions themselves are descended from
Indians so there's gonna be a similarity
in looks the the standard Persian person
has brown eyes and dark hair
and light brown skin
so lots of pakistanis and Indians look
like that
um
so that's what I have to say that
pashtoots are not descended from persons
portions are the pashtoots are part of
the extended population of northern and
western India that's what pashtoots are
yuruk says I'm from a real Turkish tribe
who came in with the seljuks in the 13th
century into turkey I'm assuming I have
physical traits nearly the same as this
man this man and also the accent is very
near you of an accent like mine you look
like me
I also had interest in interest in
Buddhism and my haplogroup is l m 2 7
l1a m i a pashtool interesting
so this gentleman Europe looks like me
nearly the same as me accent also like
me that's interesting so let's
let's take a look at this haplogroup L M
27 l1a I think it's it's it's a daughter
haplogroup of lm20 L M20
okay let's go to Wikipedia statutory
warning Wikipedia is not always reliable
often unreliable when it comes to Indian
history even Indian genetics but let's
take a look at it all the same for the
sake of convenience
haplogroup lm20
so Europe says his Hublot group is L and
27 l1a let's see
there we are L M 27 L1 A1 yes it is a
daughter haploop of l m 20.
now let's understand what lm20 is
this is where l m 20 is found it is
found in India in the Indian
subcontinent somewhat north of India
because that was part of extended India
and then you can see its offshoots west
of India including uh to some extent
Persia including in Kurdistan in Syria
in in Anatolia in Turkey in Italy in
Spain and all the way into the British
Isles and also in the north significant
amount of it is found in the uh Arabian
Peninsula then you will also see some of
it in Sumatra Java Etc where Indians
have been so clearly this is an Indian
origin haplogroup
possible time of origin 30 to 43 000
years uh it is a dissident of all this
according to Dr Spencer Wells L and 20
is hypothesized to have originated in
India about 30 years or thousand years
ago other people have said that it's a
there may be a West Asian knowledge in
all that genetics is all confusion like
this all kinds of different competing
claims most likely the origin of the
place of origin is India it's about
between 30 and 43 000 years old so if
Europe you have this haplo group it
means that you have Indian ancestors
that's what it means so you are not up
yeah Afghanistan definitely has a
significant amount of this percentage of
this but the origin is in in the Indian
subcontinent and Peninsular India most
likely so it doesn't mean you're a
person it means that you have Indian
ancestry you may and you know look my
look like me and you have an accent like
me that's that's nice to know so yeah it
means that you have Indian ancestry most
likely
okay
uh what are your thoughts on mizoram
street it's history and its culture and
also I'm a huge admirer of your work
thank you very much so thank you and
would really love to see you coming to
mizoram and other northeast states I
would love to come back I do go up there
from once in a while
uh have I been to Missouri I think I uh
I haven't actually stepped
put my put foot on the the soil the
territory of mizoram but I have landed
in isil airport I remember a hair
raising experience and you want to look
at the airport let's let's do that
so I have passed through you could say
is all
right
um you know a Transit kind of flight
let's go to the maps I hope everyone
knows where mizorab is let's go to the
Far East of India south of Manipur and
nagaland south of Manipur and tripura
and west of Burma
and yeah it has a
border with Bangladesh also so this is
mizoram as you can see this is the state
of mizoram the capital is isal I have
once passed through as all I was in the
plane I did not get off but yes it was
very scary because if you see is all
there's an airport somewhere nearby
it is uh here we have we have this
airport here
it's it's between two Hill ranges
whoa hair raising very scary experience
Landing there uh right so what do I make
what are my thoughts about mizoram State
I think it's a wonderful place the
culture is very interesting very rich
very unique culture uh I I know that
there are these Harvest festivals there
are more than one Harvest Festival
marked by festivities there is the
bamboo dance uh the the gentlemen's the
squat on the ground and they uh move the
bamboo poles around and the ladies the
dance around that it's a very
interesting uh tradition that exists
there the cuisine is interesting I don't
think the cuisine is as spicy as that
what you would find in nagaland or
Manipur uh but yes definitely
interesting Cuisine lots of non-veg
items in the cuisine uh
so I think mizoram is wonderful there is
this nice sporting culture also I think
Manipur is the sporting superpower in
the Forex but mizoram also you will find
uh footballers who come from mizoram who
play in the various Indian sporting
leagues and all that
so uh I think it's a wonderful place I I
would encourage the people from the rest
of India and the rest of the world to uh
to explore mizoram and overall the the
Faris of India the other states as well
uh and it will certainly it will be a
great experience because it's it's a
beautiful place it will also help the
local economy so I would encourage
everyone to do that I would love to come
someday to mizoram and actually visit
the state properly instead of just
touching and going off
so yeah I would love to do that and
thank you very much for uh your very
kind words
Daniel Nicholson says why does India use
a single time zone despite spanning
across two time zones from east to west
and vice versa what will be the pros and
cons of India using two time zones
instead of only one
so I would say that India needs three
time zones let's go to the map where is
the map
here's the map uh so each perfect time
zone I believe is is 15 degrees how much
what is the distance of the Equator 15
degrees I'm not quite sure maybe close
to a thousand kilometers maybe 800
kilometers not sure but it's 15 degrees
now the time zones are aren't perfect
they are they spread across countries
they're not straight lines and all so
India uses only one time zone China uses
only one time zone which is even wider
than India so I see if you if you look
at Pakistan which is north of Gujarat it
it has a time zone that's about half an
hour
after Indian Standard Time
then I believe Kyrgyzstan also has the
same sort of thing that sort of time if
you go to uh
time will be half an hour uh after India
later than India if you go to uh let's
say Bhutan or Bangladesh the time if he
is I would say most likely half an hour
ahead of Indian time you go to Kolkata
the sun sets very early
you know Sunset is very early compared
to let's say a place like Mumbai if you
go to isal or or imphal or kohima
or if you go to arunachal Pradesh
then you will find that the that the sun
rises maybe four a.m or 4 30 a.m which
is at least a couple of hours before
what it what the sunrise time is in a
place like New Delhi or Mumbai
and the sun sets also at least a couple
of hours before the sun sets in Western
India I would say that India needs three
time zones not two
and uh and you know in British during
when during the British occupation of
India
they
the city of Chennai was then called
Madras Madras time was half an hour
before Bombay time it's now called
Mumbai we know that but it was then
called Madras and Bombay so during the
British occupation of India they they
had at least I think two titles in India
Madras time was 30 minutes before Bombay
time that's how it was that made sense I
don't know why we have done this
oversimplification of the entire system
um
maybe the Magnificent history nehruji
thought that Indians are too simple into
stupid to understand time zones I think
it would be a good thing for India that
everybody has a time zone that that's
appropriate to the region I mean uh you
know if you go to the north the Far East
of India people have lunch by 10 30 in
the morning or so
maybe 10 o'clock in the morning I think
11 o'clock is too late for having lunch
and people wake up by by 4 30 or 5
that's when Dawn is so it would be good
for them to have Dawn at their seven
seven a.m or 6 45 a.m whatever whatever
is right
and so the pros are that everybody will
be able to wake up at the right time and
not be stuck to the times that of
central India because let's say you want
to do some banking transactions and the
bank closes let's say at uh 2 pm delay
time well that's
uh so that that creates problems you
know because other people have to adjust
to this time zone which is not
intrinsically correct for their region
so I would say that India needs three
time zones of Western time zone the
Western Standard Time Central Standard
Time and Eastern Standard Time the
eastern time would apply to uh Bengal
and and uh the Far East of India the
so-called Northeast of India and maybe
to the Andaman and nicobar archipelago
the Western time zone could apply to
Gujarat maybe Maharashtra Rajasthan and
Central Time Zone could be up
and uh States like Tamil Nadu
udisha and so on I think there are no
cons it may take let's say a week or so
for Indians to adjust to this Indians
aren't stupid Indians understand things
they have good intelligence
so I don't think it's going to confuse
people maybe for a few days here and
there maybe three days people will be
slightly confused but everybody adjusts
so to new realities so overall I would
say it would be good for India I don't
see any significant cons the pros will
be that everybody will be able to
function optimally in the country will
or it will be good for the country
so I think it makes sense for India to
have three time zones not just one or
not even two three is best
radio says what are your thoughts on
Fusion Energy is it possible to have
working Fusion reactors within our
lifetimes or will this just become a
failed experiment
you know
for the longest time
what scientists what physicists would
say is that Fusion Energy is 50 years in
the future so 50 years ago they were
saying that even 10 years ago they were
saying that it's always 50 years in the
future 50 years in the future Fusion is
just too difficult there have been
claims of of table top fusion and all
that but yeah that did not quite work
out
um but you know what things are changing
now now I know some people who who say
that Fusion is is gonna
it's gonna become a thing in just within
a decade that is not correct very
recently I came across a
physicist who said that uh
so what is the deal right now with
Fusion I think Fusion is a very
promising technology and
just recently we have actually achieved
ignition not we it's the Americans who
have achieved English what is ignition
so there are two kinds two ways mostly
do a try and Achieve Fusion one is a
magnetic confinement which means that
you use magnetic very strong magnetic
field to confine a plasma
in a specific region
inside your inside a machine called it
Tokamak t-o-k-a-making and that that
thin plasma
diffuse plasma you can if you make it
energetic enough hot enough and you can
find it properly enough then maybe that
will give rise to fusion and then you
can have a sustained fusion reaction uh
at a low level the other way of doing it
is inertia so that is the magnetic
confinement the other way of doing it is
inertial confinement in which you have a
pellet of Light Elements mostly hydrogen
and helium and helium-3 Light Elements
very small parent of that it has to be
almost perfectly spherical very small
pellet and you bombard that palette from
all sides with laser beams it has to be
done in a very precise manner and if you
can do it properly then theoretically
that all that laser light will will uh
will bombard enough energy into that
little pellet and cause Fusion
it'll cause a pellet to to undergo
fusion and what is ignition ignition is
when the energy that you are inputting
into this thing is less than what the
energy that comes out of the fusion
reaction that is ignition
so thus far they have been trying and
trying and trying and the energy that
they are throwing into the talent is
always way way more than the energy that
comes out of of the of the reaction in
the pellet so there is the magnetic
confinement in the inertial confinement
so recently in uh Lawrence Livermore
let's let's find the fusion breakthrough
article
let me put that on the screen so
recently what happened is that they
achieved ignition which means that the
energy that came out of the fusion
reaction was greater than the energy
that was that was put into the pellet I
think the uh
how much energy did they put in I think
2.05 Mega joules and the energy that
came out was 3.15 Mega joules or
kilojoules I don't remember uh most
likely kilojoules so 3.15 is greater
than 2.05 which means they have achieved
ignition for the first time Fusion
breakthrough is a milestone for climate
and clean energy
uh and so on so this is the uh yes
Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory
in California that's where this happened
a major breakthrough the first time it's
ever happened
so this is an article from 2022 last
year December 14. that's when it was
announced the fusion ignition is one of
the most impressive scientific feeds of
the 21st century it will go down in the
history books I agree it will definitely
go down in the history books uh so yeah
they have been trying to do this for a
very very very long time the Chinese are
they have this uh artificial sun
experiment which I believe is a Tokamak
magnetic confinement India doesn't
do any of these things for for whatever
whatever reason
so uh so yes they have now achieved
ignition The energy they shot into the
pellet
was exceeded by the energy that came out
of it so that is ignition which means
the concept works now the more energy
you slam into that thing the more energy
will come out of it
uh so it's been achieved so the theory
has been uh proven to be correct in
practice
but that is see what they have done is
uh inertial confinement in inertial
confinement the energy comes out in a
single burst boom and it's gone in
magnetic confinement the energy can be
pulled out it comes out more gradually
the fusion reaction energy
so when you do magnetic conference it's
essentially an explosion very tiny
explosion fusion reaction and all the
energy comes out in a single burst or a
single pulse and then the challenge is
how do we store that energy
because you know we have to capture that
energy and store it in some form so that
is a big challenge so we are still a
very long distance away a long way away
from a proper Fusion reactor that can
output energy on demand in a predictable
manner we are not there yet we have just
achieved ignition once maybe they may
have tried it a few more times I'm not
sure but this is this is just the
demonstration of the this is just the
proof of proof of concept
uh to harness that energy and create a
reactor uh that can store that can
output the energy repeatably predictably
is going to be the big engineering
challenge but Engineers are good
Engineers can solve most of the
challenges I would say we are still at
least 20 years away from a working
Fusion reactor and that too will be an
experimental prototype reactor for this
to become a proper technology that you
can start using to power cities and
towns and in countries will take more
than 20 years hopefully I I'm pretty
optimistic that within my lifetime I'll
be able to see a working you know
working Fusion reactors that become
commercially available but uh
it's most likely not going to be
possible in the near to Long medium term
future to have a fusion reactor that
powers your home that is not yet going
to the person maybe in the next 50 years
perhaps maybe in 100 years so most
likely by the end of the 21st century
we're going to have such reactors that
can possibly power your own house or
maybe a mini reactor that can power your
car
or your plane or whatever you know so
there's a huge amount of potential in
this I don't know why India is not
not doing anything about this I don't
know why India I don't know
there is a certain lack of ambition that
you see India which
which given the incredible intelligence
and potential
of the Indian people is very
disappointing
so yes uh all all this is kind of we can
do more that's what I would say
swapnil Mishra says a unique Celestial
event the green comet is coming what is
it and where is it how is a comet formed
and how does it end
the green comet is not coming it's
already come I think the closest
approach and the best time for viewing
was February 1. today is February 9 so
we're on at least a week past that
particular event I think right now the
comment is visible through
binoculars I don't think it's a visible
I naked eye comment
uh yeah it's been a while since we had a
comment that you could see with the
naked eye as a kid
when I was a kid I remember I witnessed
two comets in two years in 96 and 97 96
was
foreign
and 97 was Comet Hale Bob these are two
of the great comments you know very
large visible comets I believe uh Hale
Bop was greenish greenish blowish was
also a very big and visible in the night
sky you could see it with the naked eye
you don't you know they don't need a
telescope that was right there in front
of you so I went and I was very
fortunate to witness these two comments
as a kid in 1996 and 1997. and the
yakutake was discovered by a gentleman a
Japanese gentleman called yakutake who
discovered two comets in a week the
first one was never quite visible the
second one was a big one uh
so uh
so this this green comet is not I think
the best time to see it was on February
1 uh
now you may need binoculars and I'm sure
you can use some uh app
s what is it called stellarium app or
something to pinpoint where it would be
in the night sky I'm sure I could pull
up a space.com article I like space.com
they have good articles what are they
saying space.com greed comment
see here we are let's make very rapidly
put it on the screen what do they what
do they have to say about this
um
okay this was published 21 hours ago the
location of the Comet near the red
planet should make it relatively easy to
find but you will need Aid Optical
equipment telescope or binoculars so if
you know where Mars is I'm sure it's
pretty easy to locate in a dark sky Mars
is very visible it's red you know where
it is I mean I hope you know where it is
if you know what you're doing so it's
it's close to that
so this Comet will be positioned close
to Mars in the Taurus constellation
making it easier as it dims as it speeds
away from Earth the comet will appear
beside the red planet from February 9 to
February 14. so if you want to see it
that's where you will find it you can
use that stellarium or whatever software
on your it's an app I think it's an app
on your phone that you can use I'm sure
it's free if I'm not mistaken I'm gonna
use it but you can locate Mars in the
comet using that app
uh yeah so that's what you can do now
the other part of the question is um
is
how is a comet formed and how does it
end so this comment this green Comet
that is currently passing through the
inner solar system the last time it was
visible from Earth
was I think there are 50 or 60 000 years
ago
it's a very long period combat it's got
this very eccentric squashed very long
orbit so it circles around the Sun once
in about 50 or 55 or 60 000 years
the one of the most famous comments is
Halley's Comet it has a period of about
76 years so that's a very even that is
too long for us you will say if you're
fortunate twice in your lifetime not
more than that
um I wanted to see it in 85 but I was a
little kid and uh
that come Halley's comment was not quite
visible
uh
so how how is the comet formed there is
something called the old cloud
around the sun it's it's it's way far
ahead from us outside the orbit of Pluto
let's let's see what the Earth cloud
looks like a representation of that or
cloud
it's it's a giant massive enormous cloud
of of these icy bodies
uh here we are hey very small make it
larger and begin it here we are so we
know where the sun is the sun is at the
very center of this thing and your Earth
Mars a blah blah
the Earth Sun distance is called one
astronomical unit Saturn is at 10 AU
from the Sun 10 astronomical units uh
the termination shock is 10 raised to
a hundred astronomical units uh so it's
essentially past the terminal
termination shock in the interstellar
medium but it's still something that
orbits the Sun
so uh maybe 10 raised to four
astronomical units sorry for the sun all
the way almost to the next star almost
this is the logarithmic sale so it's not
quite to the next star but it's
enormously far away from the sun it's
this huge cloud of icy objects mostly
destroyed ancient uh asteroids maybe
planets that have destroyed a long long
long long ago maybe just Rocky debris
that were part of the uh protosteller
Cloud that gave rise to the sun in the
solar system maybe some of these objects
are left over from the deaths of in
older stars the previous incarnation of
the sun which spewed out this gas cloud
which then eventually coales to the
solar system
so these are very far away objects it's
Rubble it's Rubble pieces of rock mixed
with
organic material like carbon you know
things like that and ice
there's a lot of water there uh so a
comet is something that originates from
here something sometimes happens and
disturbs the objects the orbits of these
Wood Cloud objects and then they make
their way towards the Sun and once they
reach close to the sun because of the
solar wind the radiation the radiation
pressure the comet heats up and starts
releasing gas and dust and that's how it
acquires this long tail and because of
the sunlight and the radiation this long
tail starts glowing and that's why it
looks like a star with a tail from from
Earth
so it it is a it is it has a cover tail
only when it is in the inner solar
system close to the Sun once it goes
away the tail also Fades away and
disappears so that is how a comet is
formed there are trillions possibly or
billions of comets potential comets
lurking out there in the Wood Cloud once
in a while
this thing is Disturbed and one of these
things makes it its way towards the
inner solar system and that's how a
combat is formed how does the comet end
well sometimes a comet ends when it is
followed up by a planet uh there was the
great Shoemaker leaving Comet right let
me put that on the screen shoe B9
so this was a comment that slammed into
Jupiter first of what first happened is
that the gravity of Jupiter tore the
comet into pieces
so you can see those pieces of the Comet
and they're all glowing and they all
have tails that's what the incredible
gravity of Jupiter did to this to this
Comet and then in the next pass
the comet slammed into Jupiter piece by
piece by piece slam slam slam slam slam
this happened I don't know 94 yes it was
an incredible event you could see in the
the Earth astronomers captured this in
these images you can see the major scars
on Jupiter where it's been bombarded
it's been hit by the comet so that's one
way of a comment dying with it being it
hitting
a planet so Jupiter we saw this happen
maybe the impact event on Earth which
killed off the non-avian dinosaurs maybe
that could have been a comet which was
trying to make its way to the Sun but
found the Earth in the wind blank
slammed into the Earth so maybe some
Earth may have uh you know received
multiple commentary impacts in the past
another way of this happening is that
the comet is followed by the sun it
passes too close to the sun's surface it
gets torn up and then it it gets
absorbed by the Sun that is a
possibility or eventually it goes
through it makes those Cycles thousands
of millions of times eventually loses
all its material maybe it just Fades
away so these are these are some of the
ways in which a comet could end or ends
right
uh thank you sir my only request would
be that this question is for my
grandmother who gives me lots of young
knowledge but I had a question which got
me thinking and okay
trees and plants no matter where they
are growing mountains beaches valleys
planes Etc all grow in an upright
position yes more or less upright why is
this the case a tree growing on a hill
which is inclined at an angle still out
of trees growing upright correct she
questioned me and I had no answer to
give
all right so why does this happen
uh see
all the plants and trees and animals and
various species that you have today on
the planet have reached this stage this
form through Evolution evolution is the
survival of the fittest
so let's say in the past you had certain
trees that were not adapted to standing
straight and they would be tilted now if
if a tree is tilted at an angle it is
extremely disadvantageous for the tree
for survival because if you are
completely straight then you are
balanced gravity acts on both sides on
all sides and your balance at the center
of gravity is the tree trunk
so an increase of roots plants of roots
which go into the soil and anchor the
tree into the soil so if you are
standing straight completely straight
then you are at gravitational
equilibrium the forces of gravity align
properly and the center of mass is right
in the tree trunk which means you have a
great chance of living out a very long
and healthy life as a tree as long and
healthy as a tree can be so if a tree is
aligned straight
then it lives a long life it has a
higher chance of passing on its genetic
material to future generation
Generations now if a tree has the kind
of genetics that make it uh stand at an
angle then with if there's rainfall then
the roots may not be able to hold up to
the soil properly and the tree May
simply get uprooted in in collapse on
one side and then it dies or maybe
there's a storm this is the gentle storm
nothing massive that will also end the
tree's life
so I am sure in the past certain trees
would have evolved you know genetic
mutations that caused this to happen
well those trees are not around to pass
on the genetic genetic material because
those trees died out
so those genes that may have been
responsible for such characteristics
those genes were weeded out by the
process of evolution only the fittests
survive
so uh that's why
these trees they also have DNA their DNA
is programmed to make them stand
straight because that is the most
advantageous trait for long term that
ensures this survival long-term survival
of the species every species wants to
survive it wants to weed out the tree
the genetic traits that are harmful to
its long-term survival
right
so uh most likely that's what happened
it is a process of evolution that has
ensured that no matter where a tree or a
plant is whether it is on a beach or on
a hillside or a Mountainside it always
grows straight it is something that's
been programmed into the into the DNA of
trees and plants through the process of
natural selection evolution
samarth says have we ever recorded a
meteorite falling into the ocean
carrying alien biomolecules aliens or
microorganisms oh my God so scary
bacteria viruses Etc strange life forms
have we ever recorded this
hundreds of meteorites enter the Earth
every year can't this be a Potential
Threat in the form of a known alien
species Invasion which we we may
consider just a new species that we
haven't explored the oceans as well
all right
so as far as I can recall the Earth
receives between 20 to 50 to 60 maybe 80
tons of meteorite debris every day
every day
maybe between between 20 to 50 tons a
ton is a thousand kilograms
so 20 to 50 tons per day that's the
amount of meteorite material that falls
onto the surface of the Earth every
single day much of it goes into the
oceans because oceans cover two thirds
of the Earth's surface
uh we have recovered thousands of meteor
meteorite samples which are found in
scientific labs and museums across the
world
we have some in India as well
um and thus far we have we have been
able to classify several kinds of
meteorites
um
we have Carboniferous chondrites we have
Stony meteorites we have a ferrous
meteorites containing uh
iron and various other metals so there
are certain various classes of
meteorites the Carboniferous meteorites
often contain organic
chemicals
amino acids amino acids are the building
blocks of protein and protein is what
you have in your in your muscles in your
much of your body uh so you do find
organic chemistry that's present on
meteorites you find it quite regularly
um but we have never thus far
discovered a meteorite that contains
alien biomolecules or microorganisms
that would be frightfully scary it would
be a breakthrough we have never seen
before
none of the meteorite samples we have
ever
collected and studied has ever had any
life form on it of course we have the
famous uh meteorite which came from Mars
which is a Mars Rock which was which
ended up on Earth which uh seems to have
that that fossilized
bacteria like structure let's take a
look at it uh
Mars meet your right
bacteria
or a LH something the thing is called a
l h something something something
uh let's see what that is what is the
deal with that
so this is what it looks like when you
do when they took an electron microscope
image this all these tubular structures
which look like bacteria that which look
like very much like uh
bacteria that you find on Earth there
you go it's a tubular structure which is
very much characteristic of a bacillus
type bacteria
we have certain very evil bacteria on
Earth which are
broad shaped so yes that's what you see
but there is there's still a lot of
conclusive evidence that this is indeed
fossilized bacteria it looks like that
but there are alternative explanations
that have been put forth and even if
this is bacteria it is fossilized
bacteria these are not alive
these are not live bacteria
it is definitely possible that Mars
could have had life in the past
Mars was once a warm and very wet planet
we know that it's quite possible that
Mars may have had life in the past and
this uh sample did come from Mars it
originated in Mars so it's possible but
we don't have a conclusive 100
incontrovertible evidence that this
bacteria
so the answer to your question is no we
have never recorded any of these things
either alien biomolecules or
microorganisms if it happens it will be
red alert
well
let's see how that goes it's never
happened before
stupi says please explain operation
north of woods very interesting people
are discovering interesting information
operation northwards
uh it's the name that's given to this uh
proposed the false flag operation
that was proposed by the CIA in the U.S
uh
to give
the United States the pretext to go to
war with Cuba
it was I think in 1962
so at that time uh President Kennedy
was in power John F Kennedy he was the
president at the time the CIA came up
with this proposal that let's uh attack
U.S infrastructure and aircraft shoot
down a few aircraft kill some people uh
kill you know destroy some
infrastructure shoot down some ships uh
hit some ships with whatever
and make it look like the and and
pretend like it's the Cubans that have
done this then that that will give us
the justification to go to war with Cuba
so that's what was proposed
America attacking America itself the
United States attacking its own assets
maybe taking a few lives in the process
just to
acquire the pretext to go to war with
Cuba and President Kennedy flat out
rejected this he said I am not giving
you the go ahead for this
we know what happened to President
Kennedy not so soon after that let's
let's see if I can Google this up
operation northwards I'm sure there's a
nice Wikipedia article waiting for us
let's say one of the give me a second
yes the Wikipedia article as always
please remember Wikipedia is not
entirely trustworthy but this is about
the US so I'm sure it and well let's see
so operation Northwoods was a proposed
false flag operation against American
citizens that originated within the U.S
Department of Defense in 1962 The
Proposal scored for CIA okay it came
from the Department of Defense not from
the CIA but the CIA would carry it out
so the proposals called for CIA
operatives took both stage and commit
acts of violent terrorism against
American Military and civilian targets
blaming them on the Cuban government and
using it to justify a war against Cuba
you also may have heard of the Bay of
Pigs invasion which is something that
the the American deep State proposed
Kennedy said no I will not agree to this
and then they went ahead with this an
invasion of Cuba using Cuban expatriates
and then once they thought that this
will force President Kennedy's hand and
once the invasion happens and he will
agree to give Air Force and other
support to this and Kennedy refuse this
refused to give it that's why the Bay of
Pigs invention failed it was a disaster
and soon after I am not saying causation
implies correlation but soon after these
things uh Kennedy was assassinated
um
so yes that is this this uh information
about operation northwards is available
in the public domain for whatever reason
they have Declassified some of it
imagine the stuff that must be still
classified in top secret if this is
something the thought is okay to
declassify imagine the things that they
have not Declassified
you know truth can be often much
Stranger Than Fiction so that's what in
a nutshell operation Northwoods was
says most of the Cold War related books
mentioned the Cold War era Eastern
European countries as as Soviet
satellite States
but they don't mention the Western
European States as U.S satellite States
not even the Indian books it's
understandable from the Western authors
but why do the Indian authors do the
same what's their interest
this is a good question this is a good
question
yes
they speak about the Soviet satellite
States the Eastern European nations
Poland and Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia
and so on in Romania Bulgaria and you
know you know how it is the Warsaw Pact
countries so any textbook any any
history book any non-fiction book that
you pick up which mentions this this era
we'll call these nations Soviet
satellite States
but when it comes to Europe the Western
European nations they will not use such
terminology
the fact is that
the Western European nations those that
are part of the EU and NATO are U.S
satellite States
you know in the aftermath of World War
II which ended in 1945 there was a very
clear balance of power in Europe
uh the major fighting had been done by
the Soviets but at the end of the day
when almost everything was getting over
the Americans came in and they liberated
what they called what is Western Europe
uh and their armed forces their military
was stationed in various parts of
Western Europe
and eventually it's the Soviets who
entered Berlin
uh Adolf Hitler is said to have
committed suicide apparently
and and then we had the division of
Europe
into the Soviet controlled areas and the
U.S control areas
so what the Americans essentially did is
that they created a buffer zone in
Europe which is Western Europe which
came under their sway so most of the
entirety of the NATO Nations and the EU
nations are you could say American
satellite States or vasal states which
means that their foreign policy economic
policy and to some extent internal
policy
is controlled or or
influenced strongly by the U.S
especially the foreign policy especially
the defense foreign policy and post some
to a significant extent the economic
policy the internal affairs they will
most likely let it be like they will
have a hence hence a hands-off approach
as far as long as it does not uh
uh conflict with American interests
so that is the situation the Americans
created a buffer zone they were afraid
that the Soviet Union would expand
across all of Europe and that they found
it very uh very dangerous so that's why
they took these very strong robust
measures to to create a barrier Beyond
which the USSR could not at the ones
which was the Western European nations
now it is understandable why the Western
authors will write about it in this
manner they will call the Eastern
European nations Soviet satellite States
but they will call the vessel European
nations as free Nations is fiction
the U.S has nuclear weapons on the
territory of various Western European
nations do the people want those nukes
there and I'm not sure uh of course you
can also manipulate public opinion but
it is the case that the Americans have a
permanent military power presence in
Germany permanent military occupation of
Germany and Italy also and lots of other
nations invest in Europe so yes from
these perspective that's essentially the
same as the situation that was invested
in Europe during the Cold War so the
Western European nations are indeed U.S
satellite States uh the thing is in
India we only read books written in
English and the books written in English
will have the uh us version of how
things are if you were to read books
written by let's say Russian or Soviet
authors then you would see a very
different world view which would of
course be also the correct worldview why
do Indian authors do the same because
the Indian authors don't think
I'm not saying the newer authors don't
think I'm sure there are good offers
coming up nowadays but historically if
you wanted to publish a book you want to
go through Gatekeepers would ensure that
the right version of the world is put
forth in the books and if you say if you
write something that doesn't gel with
that worldview then you will not get
published no matter what you do
so
that is why Indian authors do the same
but I'm sure nowadays if somebody were
to write a book about
uh the history the the history of the
Peter of the Cold War they you would see
a different perspective perhaps I have
not come across any such thing thus far
but maybe
foreign
that's an interesting exclave of
Russia Russia
all right so where is let's go to the
map we know where Russia is
so during the Cold War we had a larger
entity called the USSR the Union of
Soviet Socialist Republics and the
Baltic Nations Estonia Latvia and
Lithuania were part of the USSR
Minsk I mean Belarus also was part of it
in Ukraine also Moldova
was also part of that now we have this
territory here
Southwest of Lithuania if I click there
it says
some District College Russia
and the the this port city here is
kalining Garden this entire territory is
called kalinindra
so this is a Russian exclaim it is not
connected to Mainland Russia
it used to be part of the USSR
so uh what is the importance so how did
um
how did it became an ex become an
exclave so after the solution of the
USSR uh Latvia Lithuania and Estonia is
clear the independence solid Baylor Rose
and so on but this region remained with
Russia it's just uh how things went now
what is the importance you can see that
this is
maybe Russia's only definitely Russia's
only port
on the Baltic Sea so it gives Russia a
window and in a staging
post for operations Naval operations
maybe maritime operations Merchant
operations in the Baltic Sea region it
is always great to have territory that
uh encompasses are a very diverse kind
of diverse geographical regions
so uh
this is a very major port and there are
other ports also so that helps Russia
with its trade activities it also helps
Russia with its military Naval
activities
and uh so that is the primary
significance oh Russia also has a
significant military non-naval presence
in uh I think they have iskandar
missiles and then these ballistic
missiles deployed there I'm sure there
will have air strips in airports here
which can be used by the Russian Air
Force
and so it is extremely advantageous for
Russia to possess this this territory
this exclave that gives them all these
advantages these ports these airfields
uh
so that is the importance of kalinandra
for Russia
garvit Singh Chauhan says where did the
original inhabitants of Australia the
non-whites originate from
uh do you believe that the trouble using
boots or did they get there as a result
of the continental drift that led to the
formation of land
we get these questions I I see these
questions very often now I understand
that our teachers do a terrible job of
teaching US history and which is why
these uh this sort of confusion is very
common to see so let me explain what the
deal is
continental drift happens over tens or
of millions of years hundreds of
millions of years understand the time
scale in the chronology
continental drift let's say the the
drift of India the Indian subcontinent
which was once attached to Africa how
did it end up in
Eurasia well plate tectonics and
continental Drift made India detach
itself from from Southern Africa and
travel all across the ocean and slam
into
Eurasia that process took roughly
120 million years
120 million years gondwara land goes
back even before that maybe 200 plus
million years
that's the super uh no Pangea was that
so continental drift is a process that
takes tens of millions of years maybe
hundreds of millions of years
Homo sapiens has been around for 200 000
years one fifth of a million years
there is no continental drift involved
in the time frame of the human species
of homo sapiens
if Homo sapiens have had been around for
200 million years then they would have
ridden the continent and drifted around
that's not the case
it's like saying that next week India
will will reach of Australia through
continental drift it doesn't happen like
that
so understand the time scales involved
continental drift of 100 years is this
long from here to here and the history
of humanity is here this much this much
tiny minuscule
so it did not happen through continental
drift please understand that understand
the time scales understand the
chronology now
let me come to the real question where
did these original inhabitants the the
so-called Australian aborigines where
did they originate from
and how did they reach Australia
let's go to the map
so the best evidence that we have the
best theory that we have is that
Humanity humans Homo sapiens originated
in Africa
if I find evidence that proves some that
shows something else I will
believe a different Theory thus far the
best evidence that we have says that
Humanity originated in Africa so how did
these people end up in Australia I
believe they reached Australia at least
six sixty thousand years ago at least
maybe 65 maybe even 70 000 years before
before today
so let's say it's 60 000 years so how
did they reach Australia 60 000 years
ago or from such such a far away
distance
so one possibility is that the
Australian Aborigines are part of the
Out of Africa migration most likely they
are part of the migration that uh
came out of Africa across the Baba
al-mandib Strait uh came into the uh
into Iran moved eastwards and then
settled down in India and from India
they went to other parts of the world
that is one possibility and then from
India they would have gone uh eastwards
uh and during the Ice Age or there must
have been multiple periods of ice ages
so at a certain point in time uh these
islands were a single land mass and most
likely at some point in time it would
have been connected to Australia through
a land bridge so that is a possibility
that they did or maybe they would have
had to do some island hopping uh using
rafts or whatever and the islands would
have been very close by so it wouldn't
not have been a very difficult very
perilous Journey that's one possibility
the other possibility is that they
actually crossed the sea itself on boats
or rafts
and we have this island right they call
it Sentinel Island North Sentinel Island
it's over here
so the people of north central island
are the last uncontacted tribe they are
a stone age tribe a small group of
people who have been living a stone age
life for at least 30 000 years so it
looks like they were crossing the sea
and somehow they got stranded on this
island and they've been here for 30 000
years
so such things do happen so one
possibility is that they did island
hopping and uh entered offering
Australia through a land bridge the
other possibility is that they actually
crossed the sea
which is extremely unlikely actually
because it's a huge distance let's say
the distance between Madagascar let's
say and Western Australia it's six
almost seven thousand kilometers that
that's almost impossible to cross unless
you have very sophisticated navigation
and you have very large boats with lots
of supplies especially food and water
and then you know how to navigate so
most likely the what happened is they
would have taken an easier way out and
uh
come through what is now the nation of
Indonesia most likely
so we still don't know exactly how it
happened but uh the presence of the
Australian the native Australians dates
back at least 60 65 000 years in
Australia that's how long they have been
there Australia belongs to the native
Australians that's that's their
territory that's their land
Sharma is Big says this question won't
apply to most people but whatever
whatever
here in Australia there's been this
controversy over the celebration of
Australia Day critics say that by
celebrating it we celebrate the
beginning of the genocide of perhaps the
world's oldest culture While others say
that by having a barbecue or going to
the beach which is how we celebrate the
occasion no one even thinks about all
the horrible things that happened on
this day what are your thoughts on this
dilemma is someone a bad person if they
have a barbecue with a friend's family
on a public holiday we also have a
national apology day for the southern
generations and its history his history
is taught in the schools now let me
address the last part first Australia
has a national apology day for the
stolen Generations what happened is that
the Australians they they stole
Aboriginal children from the parents and
they made them convert to Christianity
and they made them marry European origin
people they wanted to dilute out the
definition the race and they wanted to
subsume or absorb the Aborigines into
the white population so they stole
several generations of Aboriginal kids
from their parents imagine the
incredible trauma they would have gone
through
and they were most likely never reunited
with their parents and that's why you
have so many uh
people in Australia who have some
Aboriginal ancestry and who may not know
about this there's this cricketer Scott
bowler who recently came to know that he
has Aboriginal ancestry he thought he
was a white person yeah there's Jason
Gillespie also the so that's what the
Australian government did it was a very
racist very harsh policy for a very long
time only recently in the late 20th
century they started mending their ways
so now they have a natural apology day
which is tokenism
and they teach the history in the
schools now which is again tokenism have
with have they given any restitution
to the affected people you can't give
give any restitution or or uh
recompense or whatever it is
to people who are dead but the ones who
are The Descendants
what about them
so yeah it's it's very hard to undo the
the harms and the wrongs that have been
committed several Generations ago
but this National apology day is still
just tokenism there are lots of
Aboriginal pure blood Aboriginal people
who live in Australia today and you will
see that
alcoholism and crime and suicide are
rampant among these populations and
Aboriginal people are much more likely
to be shot for no reason by a policeman
than a white person
you know it's very similar to what
happens in the U.S where a black person
is way more likely to be harassed or
shot by police people by policemen than
a white person
so uh
a token apology day is nothing
the fact is that the
um
the Aboriginal people still face
discrimination marginalization and
oppression even today
uh their lines have been taken away the
prime lines in Australia are the coastal
lands the eastern and southern coast of
Australia let's go to the map
where's the map here is the map see the
prime territory in Australia is these
green regions
Brisbane Sydney Melbourne Adelaide
Tasmania there are no none left they've
all been murdered
so all the prime lands have been taken
over by the settlers the colonialists
and The Descendants and the majority of
the Aboriginal population lives in the
outback the very uh hot dry added
interior parts of Australia
so they're still marginalized
now
see most Nations they celebrate
Independence Day
India celebrates Independence Day the
U.S celebrates Independence Day
Pakistan has its own temporary
Independence Day and you know how it is
every nation has an Independence Day
Australia celebrates the Day of its
colonization
Australia day is it it commemorates the
the beginning of the colonization of
Australia which triggered off the
horrific genocide of the native
Australians
now the question the ethical or moral
dilemma is that should you celebrate
this day or not now most people who live
in Australia today they have done most
of them would have done nothing
to the Aboriginal people most of many of
them would not be even like they may not
even know an Aboriginal person and most
of them most likely hopefully would not
even visually harm to the Aboriginal
people but that doesn't stop them from
enjoying the fruits of the oppression in
the colonialism they live in these
wonderful parts of Australia where the
climate is great it's cool it's you know
it's it's temperate cool lots of
vegetation while the Aboriginal people
are made to live in the outback many of
them
cargurly what not the names are Alice
Alice Alice Springs
very hard places to live in and like I
said the the Australian Aboriginal
people face face a lot of Oppression
while the descendants of the
colonialists don't
even though they may not wish any harm
to the Aboriginal people they are still
enjoying the fruits
of the colonization
there are lots of people in Europe who
wish India no harm
but that doesn't stop them from enjoying
the fruits of the London of India
that's the thing uh so I don't think
it's a bad you are a bad person just
because you have a Barbie and you have a
few pints of VB or Fosters or whatever
on that day but directly or indirectly
you're celebrating the colonization the
occupation the forcible occupation of
Australia and the ensuing genocide
everything that the descendants of
colonialists enjoy today in Australia
has
has come about
through a lot
of Oppression
a lot of blood a lot of a lot of
outright genocide
so um
it's a dilemma and there's no easy
answer there's no easy way out
uh you you will have your own friend
Circle Social Circle and you know it's
just a holiday holiday to celebrate
I as a from as an individual I don't
think it's there's anything wrong with
celebrating or enjoying the occasion go
out have a Barbie have a few pints or
whatever we do but um
the way out is for the government of
Australia to give the Aboriginal people
their rights back maybe some of their
lands back
you can't say okay you can take the
entire Outback and we'll keep the nice
Prime
real estate there's a lot of
marginalization even today even though
they live in huts and Villages and all
that so as long as that situation
continues you are celebrating oppression
if if they are given equal rights and
they are given some restitution they are
given some of their lands back and they
they you're allowed you and if you allow
them to create their own Nation within
Australia
practitioner
then you can celebrate your colonization
day
see the Aboriginal people they were a
nation there were obviously lots of
different Aboriginal tribes there are
these different linguistic groups and
all that but this was their continent
so maybe
what Australia can do maybe what the
Australia the government of Australia
can do is maybe they take one-fifth of
the land of Australia as as their Nation
or as their nation state of colonized
Australia and they allow the Aboriginal
people
to create a separate nation on the rest
of the territory
that would be Justice
so they can have their own system of
government which will not be influenced
by the color the descendants of the
colonizers that would be just this even
that would not be complete in full
justice but that would be some element
some level of Justice will this happen
it will never happen
so as long as this never happens and as
long as the Australian Aboriginal people
are still oppressed
Still brutalized Still marginalized as
long as this situation continues
Australia Day still will keep on
commemorating
oppression ongoing oppression and
historical
genocide
but from a from an individual
perspective so I'm talking about the big
picture here from an individual
perspective it's perfectly fine to enjoy
any day you want including Australia Day
okay
um
let's take a different question
descendant of Rigby the clan says in
Sumerian text there is a place called
Arata whose King is
sorry I
a confidence that
nice name
some people speculate that this king
lived in Punjab or gandar well uh okay
because Sumerians also mentioned that
Arata is a very wealthy place and Julie
also found their very difficult to reach
there what's my thoughts on this
what are my thoughts about this I have
written about this I have not written
about
um but I have written about Arata uh let
me pull out my article from which year
was 2016 2017 Aryan Invasion meets India
facts
let's see
here it is let me click on there let's
pull this up and put that on the screen
this is my article from 2017.
so this is the first article I know of
that collates all the facts together all
the different pieces of evidence that
puts them together now the RN Invasion
thing is a big industry in India but I
think this is where it all starts I'm
not saying I am I I I take credit for
everything for the work everybody else
is doing there have been great Scholars
who have been doing working on this for
a very long time Dr David Frawley Dr
doctors
Conrad is lots of people have been not
of course
Dr bibilal and lots of other people so
yeah one stands on the shoulders of
giants and we must recognize the Giants
and uh yeah so this article in this
article I write about uh
here we are
so consider the both
Vedic text
uh 18.44 of this records
it's a Sanskrit Vedic text it says this
is the translation amavasu migrated
Westward his people are gandhari parshu
and Arata so this refers to a Vedic King
called amavasu whose people are the
gandhari they don't know who the Gandara
people are Gandara Afghanistan
or the Persians yes and the Arata no we
know gandar we know pursu so this guy
this King this ancient Vedic King
migrated westwards and his people are
Gandara
so it looks like the the migration that
gave rise to the
the
people of gandar and the people of
Persia and Arata so what is Arata Arata
is tentatively identified as living in
the vicinity of Mount Ararat which is uh
located in present-day turkey Eastern
Anatolia and Armenia Mount Ararat this
is the text
uh so all that is fine the traditional
Armenian name for Mount Ararat is masses
it is named after the legendary Armenian
King amasya
the name the Armenian name amasya is
linguistically related to the name
amavasu of the Indian king recorded in
the bodhya National this establishes
literary evidence of the westward
migration expansion of Indians where
Afghanistan
and through Persia into Armenia and
Anatolia
so that is literally evidence of this
place or these people the Arata people
so most likely it could be the people uh
the the ancestors of the uh Armenians
and maybe some Anatolian people uh and
Sumeria is not very far from this
region so media is essentially
present-day Iraq Etc where's the map
let's bring sumedia onto the map where's
the map where's the map where is the map
let's bring in the map
here
so we know where Armenia is I hope we
all know here it is this is Armenia
and Sumeria is is the region of of Iraq
Iraq and Syria and all that so it's
essentially the same region essentially
the same south of the region
so if Arata was the region of Armenia
then the Sumerians would definitely have
known about it because it's their
neighboring territory and I'm sure in
the old days it was very wealthy and all
that so these are my thoughts about this
matter it's most likely somewhere in the
vicinity of Armenia
or that aratha was and it was the result
of a westward migration of ancient
Indians under the king amavasu
sounds similar to the law of
conservation of energy but one is
spiritual one is philosophical what's
your opinion about this
this is a very interesting perspective
that you are giving saurabh because
karma is indeed a conservation law
the law of karma in Indian philosophy is
the
conservation
of the merits and demerits of your
actions
across multiple lifetimes
so the concept so
see in philosophy there is something
that connects philosophy with science
what is that which connects philosophy
and science you can't mix philosophy in
science please understand this
science deals with the physical world
and empirical evidence but physical
objects and then empirical evidence and
Logic the logic of mathematics
philosophy deals with physical as well
as spiritual objects and phenomena
so that's the difference
and also non-physical objects like the
soul and things like ethics and all that
but philosophy also has logic
logic
so the law of karma is the law of
conservation of the merits and demerits
of your actions across multiple
lifetimes because according to the
Indian philosophy the soul the Atma is
eternal it is part of the greater
Brahman Brahman the the great uh
Universal Atma which connects us to the
divine so it according to Indian
philosophy dharmic philosophy every
individual has a Atma which is part of
the Great Universal Atma so there is a
spark of the Divine in each of us that
is how Indians our ancestors saw the
universe and our place in the universe
so the law of karma is
the conservation of the merits and
demerits of Elections across the
lifetimes across the incarnations
through which a soul passes so even if
you die and you did bad things and good
things when you're reborn that will be
conserved and maybe you you know from
this perspective you could uh
answer why people are inequal unequal
there is inequality in the world some
people have misfortunes for no good
reason
some people have so many great talents
and characteristics why are some people
born tall and strong and handsome and
why are some people not so well blessed
maybe it is the result of karma which is
conserved across incarnations and
lifetimes you know so yes sort of a very
interesting perspective you put forth
and I completely agree with this Karma
siddhant of dharmik culture is indeed a
conservation law but not a physical
conservation law it is a spiritual
conservation law it is the law of
conservation of the merits and demerits
of the actions of a soul across
lifetimes
can you please talk about Emperor
ashoka's nine unknown men
it said that they even exist today and
people like uh Dr apj Abdul Kalam and
Isaac Newton and Albert Einstein were a
part of that
Okay so we've always had these navratnas
in the courts of various Indian Kings
and Emperors uh emperor of the kamaditya
is supposed is said to have had
navaratnas uh and other Emperors and
Kings also have had these great Scholars
and and people who typically are nine in
numbers right it's an age-old concept
in India and there was this uh this
writer called Talbot Mundy was it was he
British was he American most likely
British British
so he wrote this book called the which
I don't remember the name of the book
Maybe
I I forget the name of the book but the
author is Talbot Mundy and he wrote
about these nine unknown men and he
according to his aversion it is Emperor
Ashok who created this this system this
tradition of having nine
people who specialize who are the best
of the lot in various Specialties you
could have a musicians musicians and
people who deal with uh economics
scientists and whatnot so different
disciplines are the best of the best in
those disciplines those would be the
navratnas or the or the nine great men
and maybe they were kept secret or
hidden so that nobody would interfere
with the with their work possibly so
that's what Talbot Mundi speculated and
then this became uh this this concept
became quite famous and some people say
it's a secret society so in the old days
the navratnas were very well known
everyone knew who were the Great nine
people who were part of the court and
who are the who were the greatest of The
Emperor's respect
and patronage of
but then uh it is alleged that it became
a secret society why do we have any
evidence of this we don't have any
evidence of this
so when if somebody claims that Dr abij
Abdul kram was one of them or Albert
Einstein
I would say it's speculation we have
absolutely zero evidence of this being
the case but hey
sense of evidence is not the evidence of
absence so it's possible
uh but you know if it's indeed a secret
society and you ask me the question if I
knew about it I
foreign
all right all right
deep jit says I am pursuing Masters in
English literature somehow I feel
literature is not a subject at all it's
rather a Leisure or a hobby what I want
to get the feeling of guilt studying the
literature of our colonizers language
and I deeply regret my choice what are
your views what are my views on English
literature as a subject thank you
you know the question you have to ask
yourself when you study a subject is
when I am done studying this what can I
produce
society and civilization is built upon
production
the more Society produces the greater is
the society and the more prosperous is
the society and where a society is
sufficiently prosperous it becomes a
genuine civilization because Prosperity
brings in a great lifestyle which gives
people the time for leisure activities
like philosophy like culture like music
like literature so all these activities
are possible only when you have a high
amount of prosperity in a civilization
or culture and that Prosperity only
comes through material production
right so when you study something you
have to ask yourself when I am done
studying this when I receive my degree
what will I be able to produce
and will let's say I'm able to produce
something
will that be of any use to society
this is the question you ask
now when you study English literature
and you get a master's degree in English
literature what will be able to what
will you be able to produce
words
hopefully I mean I have known students
of English literature when I was myself
a university student
and listen
you know my feeling about the English
language I do not consider a person who
can't speak English well to be inferior
why should we be made to speak English
well okay I speak English reasonably
well it doesn't mean that I'm superior
from Superior to somebody who can't
speak English that's not the case it's
just a goddamn language it's a it's a
foreign language so if somebody can't
speak English English well it doesn't
mean that they are inferior in any sense
whatsoever they may be far better than
me in a multitude of ways so my what I'm
saying is that I have known many
students as when I was a student myself
who was studying English literature and
they could not even speak English
properly
and yet they were accepted into this
particular discipline and they even got
their master's degrees without ever
being able to speak English properly and
form a full sentence without
grammatical errors
I'm not saying it makes them inferior it
tells you how bad the English Indian
education system is
and once such a person acquires this
degree what will they produce absolutely
nothing
and let's say you are good at English
or let's say we talk about French
literature you're good at French and you
get a degree in French literature what
will you produce you will produce words
do words build a civilization
words and literature are the outcome of
a high civilization they don't build or
produce or create a great civilization
every great civilization
is characterized by wonderful literary
output
but that is only after you're able to
build a high level of prosperity when
India has been destroyed in the past
Thousand Years economically we want to
build a great civilization again which
we will
then you want to have acquired you know
study for a degree that will enable you
to be a productive
member of Indian civilization of Indian
Society so if you're studying English
literature it's indeed a Leisure
activity or a hobby literature is the
output of is the outcome of great
prosperity it's a Leisure activity it's
a hobby I'm not saying it doesn't have a
place in the world literally great
literature is is is timeless ask me look
at the books behind me I I love
literature I have read
I don't know how many books
so I'm not saying literature isn't a
good thing or it's it's a futile Pursuit
but I would say
that a very small percentage of the
population may be 0.1 percent would be
good at it and only they who see some
people are only good
at poetry
or or writing great novels and people
who are at that level should not be made
to do other work so it's only those
people who should go into English
literature or whatever literature
um yeah so that's what I feel about this
now if you have taken the subject go
ahead and study it get your degree don't
don't spend your life regretting things
get the degree and then move on into
something productive unless you are
going to be a great poet or something so
I would say that uh yeah okay maybe
maybe it's not maybe it would not have
been the best possible the most most
Optimum choice of uh
degree to study for but that's fine you
get your degree you have a master's
degree then you can get a job in other
other fields also that's what typically
happens I mean in the software industry
you find people with a bachelor's degree
in in Commerce or or a master's degree
in English literature and they end up in
software and they become programmers and
all that so it's perfectly fine it's
possible to get a career in a whole
different field than the one that you
studied
yeah but overall I agree with you that
literature is a Leisure activity it's a
hobby and only for a very small number
of people cannot be a full-time uh
field
a full full-time activity activity of
serious Endeavor for most of us it's
only going to be a Leisure activity or a
hobby
I still have more questions and I'm not
going to be able to take them as always
I try to take as many questions as
possible but I always end up short
because of the constraint of time now if
you have questions for me I will take
about five minutes of live chat
questions
and let's see if you have any questions
for me
um you know I can I can do this all
night I'm sure you will watch but uh you
have to you have to have some discipline
in life so I I remember when I was
beginning this
if you look at the first 10 20 episodes
I was I was a
doing one hour episode I should take 10
or 12 questions and I used to stop it
there
when it started going to in 90 minutes
then I started again bringing it down to
60 minutes and now I have said I've
decided I'll I'll make these episodes
roughly two hours long
so right
okay you got questions please ask me
and I will take a few questions
um
says how should we recognize the Taliban
regime they crushed Democratic Values
like women's rights media Freedom
opposition Rule and kill former
government people
yes that is indeed what they do there is
no democracy there uh women don't have
the same rights as men they you know
what happens to women there media
Freedom come
on you know maybe they'll kill some
government people yeah that's how it is
that's how it is in Afghanistan under
Taliban rule
things were much worse than China during
the initial days initial years of the
Chinese Communist party not in the same
way but in a different way
the thing is this there is no place for
sentiment in geopolitics
the government of India it has one job
to
to look out for the interests of the
Indian nation in the Indian people
and the interests are that we need to
cooperate with Afghanistan
in order to in the long term in the long
run get regain our access to Central
Asia and the rest of the world once
Pakistan is dealt with
for that we need to cultivate good
relations with whichever of our
government exists in Afghanistan
and that's what we have done very well
in the past few years so yes and see the
thing is that in in the Afghanistan we
have a different culture now it's no
longer Indian culture not for the past
1000 years
so they have a different way of life
and the I'm not sure how
um how trustworthy or reliable a Pew
Paul is Paul but a recent pupil showed
that more than 95 of the Afghanistan
people want Sharia law and they want
what Taliban is giving them offering
them
uh so you know it that's how it is
maybe most people in Afghanistan
actually do want sir yellow
so so it's not for us to judge how
things are going there
let the government of Afghanistan
whichever is in power be there and we
will cooperate with them on a nation to
Nation basis if the people of
Afghanistan feel oppressed and if they
don't like the government it is for them
to make a choice whether to overthrow
the government of not or not if they can
it's their choice and we will not
interfere in their internal matters that
has to be our official policy and that's
what we are doing
okay
uh any other questions
where did they come from and settle in
the region of Kutch I can't seem to find
accurate answers
uh thank you listen all Indians came out
of India 70 80 000 years ago they came
out of Africa India was the first
Founders zone of the Out of Africa
migrants
and from India people went all across
the world so the origin of the people of
the Indian subcontinent is the Indian
subcontinent if you go back 70 000 years
that's the origin of the Kachi people
that's it what it is that's the origin
of the Balochi people and the Kachi
people and the Sindhi people
and and the people of saurashtra and the
people of Rajasthan and the people of
Bengal and Orissa and Kalinga and the
sinhalis people are Tamil people all of
them we are all the same we have been
living in different parts of India for
God those how many generations and we
all have developed distinctive slightly
different dialects in slightly different
traditions
but we are all the same
so Kachi people did not come from
from I don't know from where you some
people imagine they came from they all
we all came out originated in the Indian
subcontinent going back at least 70 000
years
so yeah that's what it is and the origin
of that if you want to
see a slightly deeper ancestry it's the
Saraswati Sindhu phase of Indian history
that phase of Industry so I think the
people of Gujarat and Sindh are the
direct descendants of the Sarasota
people and kach is obviously part of
Gujarat it's closer
linguistically and and uh culturally to
the to sin isn't it than to Mainland
Gujarat if you could call that Mainland
but yeah
so that is the origin that's the
original that's what I can tell you
let's take maybe one more question we
are going way past the time limit
um
what do we have what do we have
why is it said that humans came from
Africa only look I would be very happy
if they came from Mars or Jupiter but
the evidence that we have says that they
came from Africa the oldest evidence
of humans not just the oldest evidence
of homo sapiens the oldest Homo sapiens
bones or fossils we have found anywhere
in the world or in North Africa in
Algeria Tunisia somewhere there the
oldest
ancestral humans that we have found are
our Homo habilis Homo erectus
[Music]
um and so on these are also all for all
found in Australia that is what the
evidence tells us in science we go about
the evidence if tomorrow we find an
older evidence of of
ancestral humans in Italy that let's see
then we will say there wasn't out of
Italy migration but as long as we don't
have such evidence we're gonna say it's
originated in Africa maybe someday we
will find evidence of older Maybe
of older uh
human bones from from somewhere else
perhaps then we will have to revise the
the the understanding based on the
evidence is always it is always driven
by evidence so the evidence says Africa
is the place where Humanity originated
so we will so that's going to be what we
accept if new evidence comes to light we
will revise our model that is how
science works there is no emotion
involved in science it's all based on
evidence empirical evidence with that I
will end today's session
thank you very much as always for all
the questions I am genuinely blessed
that so many people want me to answer
the questions I cannot answer everyone's
questions for that I apologize and I
thank you all for your viewership
and uh for watching this and I will see
you next week this week I am traveling
in the in just a couple of hours I'm
going to the airport so yeah this
weekend there'll be no live streams next
weekend I think I'll put some recorded
sessions and from the week after that
we'll be back live until then take care
all of you thank you very much once
again and uh
keep working hard keep raising your
standards and I will see you soon thank
you bye